<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Continuation of our weekely intelligence since the 22. of this present moneth, to the 29. The second part containing many notable and very remarkeable passages, amongst the rest, you shall finde these, the strange and vnexpected reduction of the city of Prage in Bohemia ..., the taking whereof (with Gods assistance) was performed by the old Count of Thorne ..., the great preparation of the B. of Collen ... and other leagers, to joyne with the imperiall scattered troopes ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2828</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">25208454</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 25208454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27882</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08147)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27882)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1857:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Continuation of our weekely intelligence since the 22. of this present moneth, to the 29. The second part containing many notable and very remarkeable passages, amongst the rest, you shall finde these, the strange and vnexpected reduction of the city of Prage in Bohemia ..., the taking whereof (with Gods assistance) was performed by the old Count of Thorne ..., the great preparation of the B. of Collen ... and other leagers, to joyne with the imperiall scattered troopes ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Butter and Nicolas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: The Continuation of our weekely newes : from Prage the 4. of November, 1631.</note>
                  <note>"November 29. Numb. 1."</note>
                  <note>"[Eighth Series.]"--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648.</term>
               <term>Prague (Czech Republic) --  History, Military.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27882:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>November 29.</p>
            <p>Numb. 1.</p>
            <p>THE CONTINVATION OF OVR WEEKELY Intelligence ſince the 22. of this preſent moneth, to the 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Part. Containing many notable and very remarkeable paſſages, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, you ſhall finde theſe,</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The ſtrange and vnexpected reduction of the City of <hi>Prage</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to its ancient liberty and freedome, from the cruell tyranny of the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> vnder the Command of that ſuparlatiue bloudy tyrant the D. of <hi>Freedland,</hi> and others, together with the like free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome begun over the whole Kingdome, by a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall revolt and club Law in all parts, where they doe but meete with any <hi>Imperialiſts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The taking whereof (with Gods aſſiſtance) was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the old Count of <hi>Thorne,</hi> and other <hi>Bohemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> baniſhed Lords, Commanders of ſome <hi>Swediſh</hi> and <hi>Saxon</hi> forces and other, the poore oppreſſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues entertaining this occaſion as ſent them from God, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>The great preparation of the B. of <hi>Collen,</hi> the Arch-duke <hi>Leopaldus,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and other Leagers, to to joyne with the <hi>Imperiall</hi> ſcattered troopes, (for now there is no diſtinction) to recover if it may be (that by multitude,) what ſmall and weake meanes hath taken from them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath: Butter</hi> and <hi>Nicolas Bourne.</hi> 1631.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27882:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27882:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27882:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Continuation of our Weekely NEWES.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Prage</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> of <hi>November, 1631.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Citie is every where exceedingly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and amended. Great feare alſo is conceived in this place, wherefore, men tranſport their goods and flie to <hi>Vienna.</hi> For the Duke of <hi>Saxons</hi> Forces are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quartered in this Kingdome of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and doe encroach day by day vpon vs. As alſo the <hi>Swediſh</hi> are fallen into <hi>Sileſia</hi> at leaſt fifteene thouſand ſtrong, where they haue taken <hi>Great Glogaw</hi> of late and divers other places of moment. Yea they haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues in a victorious manner, even before <hi>Breſlau.</hi> Which hath cauſed the Emperours forces mainly to intend againſt them. Who with all expedition are marching to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them.</p>
               <p>His Imperiall Majeſtie this day, as alſo divers times of late himſelfe in perſon hath beene preſent in the Counſell of Warre, and with them conſulted, how and by what meanes a mightie Armie may ſpeedily be raiſed. To this effect the Lord <hi>Queſtenburg</hi> is ſpeedily ſent to the Duke of <hi>Freid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Commiſſions are graunted from his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, for the levying and raiſing of an hundred thouſand men.</p>
               <p>The Chancelor of the Duke of <hi>Lunenburg,</hi> Lord of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern,</hi> who had with him many confiſcated goods in <hi>Ellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boger</hi> Countrey; was ſurprized in the night, carryed away; and the ſaid goods are reſtored to the former poſſeſſors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27882:4"/>
               <head>From <hi>Yſleben</hi> the <hi>1.</hi> of <hi>November, 1631.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Laſt weeke the Imperiall Commaunder <hi>Bunnickhouſen,</hi> with his Cavalleries, fell vpon ſome of his Majeſtie of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> forces, and defeated them in a certaine Village where they lay. On the other ſide the Lieutenant Generall <hi>Schaſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> ſurpriſed three Companies of Imperiall horſemen, and vtterly defeated, yea, ſlew them all, ſome few excepted which fled into <hi>Magdenburg.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Rotenburg</hi> the <hi>8.</hi> of <hi>November.</hi> In the Country of Franconia.</head>
               <p>From <hi>Erfort</hi> is confirmed that ſince his Majeſtie of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> hath taken the ſame Citie, it is exceedingly oppreſſed with Garriſons, more then the Citie is able to beare. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon thoſe of the Citie by their Committies, haue made humble ſute to his Majeſtie of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to the end they might be eaſed and disburdened of ſo intollerable a Charge.</p>
               <p>His Majeſtie intends to ſend his Queene thither to reſide there, whom they daily expect. Others are of opinion, that the Queene ſhall keepe her reſidence in the Caſtle of <hi>Wirtſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> which indeed is a ſtrong and Royall Caſtle.</p>
               <p>In all parts here abouts, are levied all Souldiers that vpon any termes will beare Armes, both horſemen and foote.</p>
               <p>Two dayes agoe we heard a great thundring of ſhooting. Whereupon we doe preſume, that the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and the Generall <hi>Tillies</hi> Army, haue had ſome ſore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter neare vnto <hi>Mergenheym,</hi> which is very probable to be ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Lauſenitz</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> of <hi>November.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The <hi>Imperiall</hi> Garriſons in <hi>Bautſen, Garlitz,</hi> and <hi>Sitta,</hi> durſt in no wiſe expect the comming of the Duke of <hi>Saxons</hi> Army; wherefore they haue abandoned <hi>Lauſenitz</hi> wholly, and haue betooke themſelues into <hi>Sileſia.</hi> Which indeede happened with great confuſion, in ſo much that they were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27882:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſtrained (by reaſon of their perplexitie) vto leaue the chiefe of their Ordnance at <hi>Gorlitz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> his Army purſued the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts, even at the heeles, and the ſaid <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken by the <hi>Saxons</hi> neare vnto <hi>Hirſchbergh.</hi> But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> durſt not ſtand to it, they were ſlaine by wholes troupes of them, and miſerably deſtroyed, as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you will ere long vnderſtand by a more ample Relation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Out of <hi>Franconia</hi> the <hi>9.</hi> of <hi>November.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>His Majeſtie as yet is reſident at <hi>Wirtſburg,</hi> which he hath cauſed to be exceedingly fortified; in the night he takes vp his lodging in the Caſtle. Some of <hi>Tillyes</hi> Souldiers who are impriſoned by the <hi>Swediſh,</hi> affirme, that there is exceeding great want in the Popiſh Army, both of Victualls and other proviſion. Whereupon the Souldiers doe faint, and let their courage ſinke. They confeſſe that many impotent forces are aggregated confuſedly together, but to no great purpoſe, neither in any good order. Neither are they able to furniſh their Armie with Ordnance and Munition, &amp;c. ſince that horrible overthrow neare vnto <hi>Leipſich.</hi> Eſpecially they are weakened exceedingly, becauſe his Majeſtie of <hi>Sweden</hi> hath taken (of late) <hi>Wirtſburg,</hi> and other ſtrong places, furniſhed with all manner of neceſſaries. And doth daily proceede in his Victorious and ſucceſſefull proceedings. Whereas the <hi>Catholike League,</hi> haue not time to conſult of the maine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, much leſſe to prevent the common danger and miſery, which now comes flowing vpon them in full ſtreame, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one hath enough to doe, to ſhift for his owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſafetie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Hanaw</hi> the <hi>11.</hi> of <hi>November.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I doubt not but you haue heard how this Citie hath beene ſurprized and taken by the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> forces. Giue me leaue briefly to relate it vnto you, if happily you are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the manner of it.</p>
               <p>In the morning early, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1. three thouſand <hi>Swediſh
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27882:5"/>Dragoners</hi> (Muſquetiers on Horſebacke) and ſix hundred <hi>Curaſſiers,</hi> came before this Citie, and entred and paſſed through the Kinzing gate, where they patarded the Gate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the Caſtle, and ſcaled the wals, ſo that by theſe meanes they ſoone maſtered the Old Citie. In this furious aſſault and expedition, onely eight Citizens and three Souldiers were ſlaine, beſides ſome other hurt.</p>
               <p>The Earle of <hi>Hanaw,</hi> (notwithſtanding his Counteſſe was then in Labour, or at leaſt-wiſe newly brought to bed of a young daughter) was preſently taken in hold. And preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after aſſaulted the New Citie furiouſly, and battered vpon the ſame with Canon ſhot. Thoſe within reſolved to defend themſelues to the vttermoſt. But being threatned with ſore threats, were at laſt willing to come to agreement, appealed to the Earle, and required his conſent, who came to them vpon the walles of the Citie, and ſpake to them in the Citie, in this manner.</p>
               <p>My faithfull and loving Citizens and Souldiers, to affoord you much Counſell in this extremitie, or any aſſiſtance, I am not able, by reaſon I am a priſoner. Onely this I wiſh you to compound and make your agreement vpon the beſt termes you can. Which they willingly conſented vnto, and did ſo. And thoſe that would betake themſelues into the ſervice of his Majeſtie were entertained; the reſt were impriſoned. His Majeſtie of <hi>Sweden</hi> himſelfe in perſon was not in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, but is daily expected at <hi>Hanaw,</hi> to eſtabliſh order according to his Royall Direction.</p>
               <p>The forces of the Generall <hi>Tilly</hi> which were enquartered at <hi>Heuxt, Hofſteym,</hi> and other places hereabout, haue aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned their Garriſon, and are fled to <hi>Mentz.</hi> The <hi>Swediſh</hi> haue alſo taken <hi>Fryburgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As many Forces as poſſibly can be are raiſed for the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke League,</hi> in this their extreame need, and to this end divers Officers are ſent into the Land of <hi>Liege,</hi> to levie ſome Troupes.</p>
               <p>The Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold</hi> is now alſo about to levie an Army of 20000 men. And as we are credibly enformed, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27882:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Biſhop of <hi>Cullen</hi> himſelfe in perſon will come into the field with his new Army.</p>
               <p>We haue ty dings that the City of <hi>Straſburgh</hi> is agreed with the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> likewiſe <hi>Norinburgh, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lme</hi> and other Cities are upon termes of compoſition. Colonell <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger</hi> is ſent to the forenamed Cities, as Commiſſary for his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to agree with them as he ſhall finde it conſonant. The ſame Commiſſary met in his journey with a Wagon full of Spirituall Perſons, neare vnto the City <hi>Vlms,</hi> all which he tooke hold of, and ranſomed them afterwards for 40000 Rix-Dollars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Swynfordt</hi> the <hi>10</hi> of <hi>November.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Laſt Wedneſday his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> of <hi>Sweden</hi> with 33 Cornets of Horſe, accompanied with divers Earles, and other great Lords and Peeres, departed from <hi>Wurtſburgh,</hi> and is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gone to the Army newly levied neere vnto the City <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſtadt,</hi> by the River <hi>Mayne,</hi> there to adjoyne his Troupes with them.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Maieſtie</hi> tooke along with him from this place, 4 Companies, and as many as he could well ſpare from ſome other places, by reaſon he had information that the <hi>Imperiall Forces</hi> were ſpeedily marching toward <hi>Carelſtadt,</hi> againſt the ſayd new raiſed Army. They are already come neere vnto <hi>Niewſtadt,</hi> and <hi>Rotten,</hi> where doubtleſſe when they meete, ſomething will be effected.</p>
               <p>This City, as likewiſe the Caſtle of <hi>Wurtſburgh</hi> is much fortified. His <hi>Maieſtie</hi> cauſeth a new Army of 40000 men to be raiſed, to which end, both here, and in all the adjoyning Countries the Drummes beate, and the Trumpets doe ſound continually.</p>
               <p>In the mean while tis a great miſery that befals theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and none without pitty or compaſſion can either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold or heare of the ruines in theſe Parts. Men haue heavy taxations laid vpon them, and great contributions muſt be paid; but eſpecially by the Clergy, which cauſeth both Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Clergy to abandon their reſidence, which is pilladged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27882:6"/>and ſpoyled by the Souldiers in their abſence.</p>
               <p>Newly we received tydings that the whole <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aunt-guard</hi> of the <hi>Cavallerie</hi> of Generall <hi>Altringer</hi> is vtterly defeated, and many of them ſlaine. Inſomuch that no leſſe then 6. Cornets were brought and preſented to his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> we ſhall acquaint you with the particulars the very next occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Torgan</hi> the <hi>9</hi> of <hi>November.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> not daring to abide the Encounter with the <hi>Saxon</hi> Forces, haue quite left and forſaken the ſix Cities in <hi>Luſatia,</hi> and are fled into <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> there if they can to defend thoſe Countries.</p>
               <p>Since that an Ambaſſador from his <hi>Imperiall Maieſtie</hi> with a great traine of followers is arrived at <hi>Dreſden,</hi> with very friendly and patheticall moving Letters to our Prince Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> which Letters ſound to this effect, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That it never was his <hi>Imperiall Maieſties</hi> intention or will, to make the incurſion into <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and that he for his part, hath no other cauſe (but after great experience) to be well aſſured of his <hi>Maieſties</hi> favour and loue: Knowing what a friend his <hi>Imperiall Maieſtie</hi> hath beene to him, inſomuch, that he could not expect any emnitie at his hands, onely if he would be pleaſed to lay downe, and abandon his Armes. But ſince our Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> ſufficiently knowes his <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſties</hi> diſpoſition, by woefull proofe and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, eſpecially ſince matters are now come to this high paſſe, the Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi> will not truſt to his coloured proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but earneſtly adde further proceedings to their good beginnings, and leaue the iſſue to the <hi>Almightie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Leypzich</hi> the <hi>12</hi> of <hi>November.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>His Highneſſe of <hi>Saxonie</hi> at this preſent is at <hi>Bautſen</hi> in perſon, but his chiefe Army is in <hi>Bohemia.</hi> The <hi>Swediſh</hi> of <hi>Croſſen</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> haue taken great <hi>Glogaw,</hi> and ſlaine all the Souldiers there that made any oppoſition.</p>
               <p>It is moſt certaine, that 12000 <hi>Swediſh</hi> more are now ſpeedily marching to his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> about <hi>Wurtſburgh,</hi> to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his <hi>Maieſties</hi> Army.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27882:6"/>
               <head>From <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> the <hi>13.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>A few dayes agoe the Garriſon of <hi>Roſtocke</hi> came before this City, and required 4. dayes proviſion. Which by the Magiſtracy of the City was refuſed: they profeſſed that they would cleave cloſe to the Concluſion made at the Dyet at <hi>Leypzich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſame Guarriſon are adjoyued eleven Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net more, whether they will now tend will ere long appeare.</p>
               <p>The Earle of <hi>Gransfield</hi> is now leuying of an Army in <hi>Weſtphalia.</hi> He is come into the Byſhopricke of <hi>Minden</hi> with the Regiment of <hi>Erwitz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Commander <hi>Baninghouſen</hi> Colonell of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd 11. troupes of horſe, (beſides the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of <hi>Magdenburgh</hi> and <hi>Wolfenbuttle</hi>) hath brought againe all places unto <hi>Halberſtadt</hi> under Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thoſe that will not contribute, he puts them to fire and ſword. He hath alſo ſorely threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Halberſtadt,</hi> but whereas divers troupes of Swediſh are newly come thither, he will availe but little with his enterpriſe. The ſame Commander hath pillaged 14. Wagons laden with good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities going from <hi>Hamburgh</hi> to <hi>Leypzig.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Breme</hi> the <hi>17.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>Our Byſhop cauſeth all poſſible ſtrength to be brought together, to extirpate <hi>Tillyes</hi> forces out of theſe quarters, he hath already incorporated two places. And as it is reported, the Garriſon of <hi>Staden</hi> hath againe taken <hi>Boytſenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Lauwenburgh,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Collen the <hi>16.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>Sixe hundred of Swediſh Horſe-men, marched
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27882:7"/>neare unto <hi>Franckfort</hi> the 13. of this Moneth. Theſe in paſſing by related, that whereas the Emperialiſts had utterly abandoned <hi>Luſatia,</hi> that the D. of <hi>Saxony</hi> hath taken the 6, Cities in thoſe Countries, and ſo is marched forward toward <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Letters from <hi>Leypzig</hi> affirme the ſame, and moreover that he is now Maſter of, and hath ſubdued the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>Limaris,</hi> and is come within ſome 7. Miles from <hi>Prague,</hi> and hath taken the City <hi>Litmaris.</hi> Which hath a bridge over the River <hi>Elve,</hi> ſo that now there is no more reſiſtance but onely a plaine open way to the City of <hi>Prague.</hi> The old Earle of <hi>Thurne</hi> and divers other Dutch Lords, have adjoyned their ſtrength to them.</p>
               <p>The Proteſtant Peeres have willingly contributed in the Concluſion at the Dyet at <hi>Leipzich</hi> as here followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Strasburgh.</hi> 279000, <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rimbergh.</hi> 478800. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Worms.</hi> 065560. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wirt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mburgh.</hi> 043720. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lindow.</hi> 029760. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nordlingen.</hi> 054600. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Swabiſh Hall.</hi> 098443. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Heylbrun.</hi> 644800. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lm.</hi> 179000. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Memmingen.</hi> 051163. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Kempten.</hi> 048360. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rotenburgh</hi> on the <hi>Tauber.</hi> 011780. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sweinfurt.</hi> 054880. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wirtzenheym.</hi> 052080 <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Weiſſenburg.</hi> 031000. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Summe,</hi> 2312146. <hi>Gilders.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Eger</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the <hi>5.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>Here is great flight in this Kingdome from all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27882:7"/>parts, and men tremble for very feare, becauſe the Swediſh fall furiouſly into all places, and have alree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy conquered many brave Lordſhips and ſtrong pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. It is alſo moſt certaine, that <hi>Ioachims</hi> Valley is taken by the Swediſh.</p>
               <p>The Lantgrave of <hi>Heſſens</hi> forces have made ſhort worke in <hi>Paterborne,</hi> where they found but ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. Some Spaniſh troupes are paſſed by <hi>Duy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,</hi> and are marched towards the Palatinate. Thoſe of <hi>Mentz</hi> have taken into their Citty 4. Spaniſh Companies, and have enquartered ſome troupes in <hi>Ringnow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Bergen-up-zoom</hi> the <hi>18.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>From <hi>Antwerpe</hi> is written, that 8. <hi>Turkiſh</hi> men of warre from <hi>Algiers,</hi> were fallen into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and from thence carried away captive 1500. men, which they thought to have brought into <hi>Algiers,</hi> &amp; ſold them: but 12. Dunkerk men of warre met them by the way, and after a long fight ſunke two of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> men of warre, and tooke 6. more, and threw all the Pyrates overboord, ſo that the <hi>Friſh</hi> are all reſcued from ſlavery, and landed againe in <hi>Freland.</hi> Which we muſt expect ſome confirmation of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we aſſure it true.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Antwerpe</hi> the <hi>17.</hi> of November. <hi>1631.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For newes, by the Letters come this day from <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many:</hi> ſome men have writte from <hi>Norimbergh,</hi> that the Duke of <hi>Saxonyes</hi> forces ſhould have taken in <hi>Prague,</hi> it doth agree with that one writteth me from <hi>Hambrough,</hi> how that the D. of <hi>Saxony</hi> with his whole Army was entring into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and was within 7. leagues of <hi>Prague,</hi> (it ſhould ſeeme Count <hi>Thurne</hi> was the leader of them) the King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> continues in his late conquered places, where he makes himſelfe ſtrong, and gathers in great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27882:8"/>in the Townes and Countries therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts; <hi>Tilly</hi> hath a great number of men, but moſt of them unexperienced in warres: the King hath ſent the Count of <hi>Solmes</hi> into <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> to have their preſent reſolution, whether they will take in his ſouldiers to Garriſon; <hi>Tilly</hi> hath ſent one to them to perſwaded them to take in the Emperors Souldiers, they would be happy if they could refuſe both and remaine neutrall and friend to both; but it ſeemes they muſt reſolve the one or the other; judge you in what a predicament they live, for they would faine hold with the ſtrongeſt, and that is doubtfull, ſo long as they have both ſtrong Armies in the field: It ſhould ſeeme, that the Biſhop of <hi>Breame</hi> takes time while time is, and begins to put the Emperors Souldiers out of his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction. Many doe write that the neather Circle of <hi>Saxony,</hi> will have 12000. men in the field, and the <hi>Hance</hi> Townes like to Arme them; ſo that by all appearance this next Summer all <hi>Germany</hi> will be up in Armes: for particular fightings, many write of many, but they are farre from hence, and therefore forbeare to write of any of them: It ſhould ſeeme the <hi>French</hi> are already marching towards <hi>Italy,</hi> they ſay to put into Garriſon; I doe believe ſo till the next Spring, and then will ſhow their intents; for there is a generall opinion they will joyne with <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the next Spring goe into <hi>Italy:</hi> and make a pretended warre againſt <hi>Germany,</hi> and get <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> if they can; the next yeare is like to be bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, God ſend a good peace to prevent ſo great a bloudſhed as is like to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:27882:8"/>
               <head>Extract of another Letter of the <hi>18.</hi> of November. <hi>1631.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY Gods aſſiſtance the old Count of <hi>Thurn,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſome <hi>Swediſh</hi> forces and ſeconded by ſome troupes of the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with many Bohemian Lords and Noble-men, that by the Emperour were baniſhed, tooke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any oppoſition the Metropolitan City of <hi>Prage,</hi> of whoſe comming as ſoone as the Governour of the Caſtle and the other of the Towne had notice, they both with many more chiefe Miniſters and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers had no mind to ſtay for that Earle his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but ſaved themſelves by flight.</p>
               <p>They were followed by many Ieſuites, Fryars and Prieſts, who all went towards <hi>Paſſan</hi> and into <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Fridland (Walſteyn)</hi> did indeed ſhew great diſpleaſure at their flight. But ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he himſelfe and <hi>Don Balthazor</hi> (who commands all the milice and gariſons in Bohemia) faining as if they would goe foorth to meete and parly with the ſaid Earle of <hi>Thurne,</hi> they were no ſooner out of towne but went alſo away as faſt as they could towards <hi>Budwize.</hi> Therefore ſome of the Swediſh Army joyning with many Bohemians, who are glad of ſo good an opportunity to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againe from the inſupportable yoke, both their conſciences and goods are under, doe follow them, to hinder them to make any conſiderable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Almoſt all Townes doe openly reioyce and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare for them, and ſo all <hi>Bohemia</hi> doth make a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall inſurrection, in manner, that whereſoever the people meetes with an Imperiall ſouldier, or whom they doe but ſuſpect to be an Imperialiſt, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently knocke him downe.</p>
               <p>And how this new conqueſt doth pleaſe the Duke
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27882:9"/>of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and the Emperour himſelfe, may well be ſuppoſed. The ſaid Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with about 12. thouſand men to draw and march towards the Papiſts Army (for the Imperiall and Leaguiſh are ioyned into one, and <hi>Tilly</hi> doth no more appeare alive) when the newes of Bohemia did cauſe him to make a ſtand and to take new Counſell. This we underſtand for certaine, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Out of another Letter the <hi>14.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>I Doe not doubt but you have heard that the Count of <hi>Thurne</hi> hath delivered againe both <hi>Prague</hi> and many other parts and places of <hi>Bohemia</hi> from the oppreſſion they have ſighed under theſe many yeres. I hope to ſend you by the next more particularities thereof.</p>
               <p>Meanewhile I will tell you, that a friend of mine writes to me, that Generall <hi>Tilly</hi> fell ſo ſicke the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day of his overthrow before <hi>Leypſich,</hi> that ever ſince all the skill of Surgeons and Phyſitions could not keepe him alive. And ſo I am ſure that hee is dead, but I cannot (as yet) tell you when and where he dyed.</p>
               <p>The Roman Catholike Army, lying ſtill for the moſt part betwixt the <hi>Rhine</hi> and the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> doe by incurſions now and then great hurt therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, not againſt their Enemies, but onely upon the poore people, burning ſpoiling and ſacking all whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they can come. For there is no diſcipline, nor order, nor Religion amongſt them. They have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken ſome places (of no ſtrength) in the Marqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat of <hi>Onſpach,</hi> and the very towne of <hi>Onſpach;</hi> yea they are not content to burne and rob the houſes and the poore Countrey-people, but they have of late beene ſo barbarous that they have opened the Monuments and Sepulchers of the Princes and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27882:9"/>of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> that governed at <hi>Onſpach,</hi> and there robbed the dead and abuſed the corpes, which ſome Finlanders underſtanding ſwore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, ſaying; they were but ſorry to have to deale with ſuch as durſt ſhew no courage againſt them, but were onely fit to rob and boaſt againſt the dead Lyons, whom they never dare looke in the faces whileſt they are alive; And that they being fitter for the gallowes then for an Army, they hoped to meet them once againe as they had lately done in their quarter neare <hi>Leypſich,</hi> where <hi>Tilly</hi> had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen his quarter due to his robbers, and where they receiued their reward.</p>
               <p>Landgrave <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Heſſen</hi> being come backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine out of <hi>Paderborn</hi> to <hi>Fulda,</hi> hath brought with him thither many principall and Noble-men of that Biſhoprick, as hoſtages, untill all the contributions agreed upon ſhall be payd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bannier</hi> (who is now Generall commanding a Swediſh Army in the Countrey of <hi>Magdenburgh</hi>) hath blocked up the ſaid Citty, ſo that it is hoped he will bring the ſame againe into the former liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and deliver it from the Cruell Vſurpators.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From <hi>Antwerp</hi> the <hi>27.</hi> of November.</head>
               <p>This Inſtant there is a good friend of ours come from <hi>Franckford</hi> poſt in 3. dayes, who confirmes the taking of <hi>Hanaw,</hi> and ſayth that for certaine, <hi>Prague</hi> is taken, with all the Citties Townes and places thereabouts, by the Duke of <hi>Saxony.</hi> And the King of Swedlands forces are marched from <hi>Hanaw</hi> to <hi>Franckford,</hi> which undoubtedly muſt alſo yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, in fine the King of Swedland is very victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and in all poſſibility to conqver all <hi>Germany,</hi> and the Empire: when I have any more newes, I will not faile to perticipate it unto you.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
